Finding Aid for the Collection of Turkish Manuscripts LSC.0896
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Title (Romanized): [Risale-i t?p] Title (English): [Treatise on Medicine], Date: [17--]?; Manuscript number: 172; 95 leaves: paper; 204 x 146 mm. bound to 203 x 150 mm.; Layout: Average 23 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Soft brown leather, blind-stamped, with leather stripe over s
  The manuscript begins with a treatise on medicine, purportedly in 40 chapters. However, the chapter headings are not numbered after 38, and the un-dotted heading "bab" (chapter), continues up to 33b. Thenceforth another title begins with medical stories from Alexander and Bahram. The ending (ff. 79a to the end) contains several prayers and recipes.
- Title (Romanized): Makamat-i evliya Title (English): Lives of the masters Alternative titles: ?????? ?????, Date: 1716; Manuscript number: 173; 48 leaves: paper; 198 x 147 mm. bound to 197 x 145 mm.; Layout: Average 18 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q & Naskh. Binding: Marble paper on boards and brown leather, with orange paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; enclosed inred borders. (Box 49)
  Abd al-Qadir al-Jilani, d. 1166
  Treatise on Sufism and Sufi master. The manuscript contains four other titles.
- Title (Romanized): Ilm-i t?p Title (English): Science of medicine Alternative titles: ??? ??, Date: [17--]?; Manuscript number: 174; 27 leaves: paper; 197 x 142 mm. bound to 197 x 147 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Pink marble paper on boards, and yellow paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; enclosed in red borders. (Box 49)
  A treatise on medicine, divided into a theoretical section (nezerî) and practical one (amelî).
- Title (Romanized): Serefü'l-insan Title (English): The nobility of man Alternative titles: ??? ??????, Date: 1586 February; Manuscript number: 175; 140 leaves: paper; 205 x 154 mm. bound to 207 x 166 mm.; Layout: 28 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 49)
- Title (Romanized): Gayetü'l-beyan fî tedbiri'l-insan Uniform title: al-?ibb al-mujarrab: al-musammá Ghayat al-itqan fi tadbir badan al-insan Title (English): The utmost eloquence in the treatment of people Alternative titles: ???? ?????? ?? ????? ??????, Date: [17--]; Manuscript number: 176; 272 leaves: paper; 199 x 111 mm. bound to 202 x 120 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faux black Morocco. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b and beginning end-paper illuminated. (Box 49)
  Encyclopedic treatise on diseases and cures, composed during the reign of the Ottoman Sultan Mehmet IV (1648-1687).
- Title (Romanized): [Shar?] al-risalah al-waqíah fi ilm al-fara'i? Title (English): [Commentary] on the right treatise on the science of inheritance Alternative titles: ??????? ??????? ?? ??? ???????, Date: 1705; Manuscript number: 177; 184 leaves: paper; 211 x 150 mm. bound to 210 x 150 mm.; Layout: Average 20 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh & Nastál?q. Binding: Blue marble paper with black leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; formulas; paper tipped in. (Box 49)
  ff. 21b-42b: A commentary on an original text about inheritance laws written by a certain A?mad Qr(?)shahri (K?rsehri?). The manuscript contains several other short and long treatise, in Turkish and Arabic, in several hands, and on several different kinds of papers, dealing with inheritance and the arithmetic thereof.
- Title (Romanized): [Kitap-i t?p] Title (English): [Book of medicine], Date: 1594 June; Manuscript number: 178; 165 leaves: paper; 211 x 155 mm. bound to 205 x 154 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black leather, blind-stamped; separated. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, several leaves missing from the beginning. (Box 49)
  Medical book, comprising chapters on various disease and their cure.
- Title (Romanized): Dürretü't-taç Uniform title: Dürret üt-taç Title (English): Pearl of the crown Alternative titles: ??? ?????, Dürret üt- taç fi sahib-ül miraç, Date: [17--]?; Manuscript number: 179; 387 leaves: paper; 206 x 125 mm. bound to 204 x 135 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Green cloth on boards, with fore-edge flap, and green paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, contained in red borders; 1b, 97b, 183b, and 185b illuminated. (Box 50)
  Veysî's biography of the prophet Muhammad. The manuscript also contains the continuation of this text by Yusuf Nâbi.
- Title (Romanized): Tezkeretü'l-mesâyih Title (English): Remembrance of the masters Alternative titles: ????? ???????, Tezkeretü'l-evliya, Date: [14--]?; Manuscript number: 180; 300 leaves: paper; 201 x 143 mm. bound to 201 x 148 mm.; Layout: 14 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped; with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, leaves separated from the beginning and missing from the beginning and the end. (Box 50)
  This is an early Ottoman translation of the biography of Sufi masters by Farid al-Din A??ar.
- Title (Romanized): [Hikayet-name] Title (English): [Story book], Date: Before 1590; Manuscript number: 181; 435 leaves: paper; 201 x 131 mm. bound to 201 x 138 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Orange marble paper on brown leather, with pink paste-downs, and fore-edge flap partially torn. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 50)
  Note on 1a establishes terminus ante quem
  A collection of strange tales culled by the author from choice histories in Arabic and Persian and translated into Turkish.
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i] Silsiletü'z-zeheb Title (English): [the translation of] the Chain of gold Alternative titles: ????? ?????, Date: 1855; Manuscript number: 182; 30 leaves: paper; 244 x 176 mm. bound to 245 x 177 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Blue marble paper on boards, with burgundy leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink; marginalia. (Box 50)
  Treatise on the authorities in the chain of transmission of prophetic Hadith. Purportedly translated from an Arabic original by Mu?ammad ibn Ismai Bukhari (810-870). The manuscript also contains the continuation of the same text by the translator.
- Title (Romanized): [Ilm-i Faraiz] Title (English): [Science of inheritance] Alternative titles: Incipit: Tereke-i meyyite hukuk-i erbaa taalûk ider, Date: No date; Manuscript number: 183; 85 leaves: paper; 235 x 168 mm. bound to 233 x 167 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: brown paper. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked words in red; charts and formulae. (Box 50)
  The manuscript contains two brief treatises on inheritance, up to leaf 9b. These begin with: Tereke-i meyyite hukuk-i erbaa taalûk ider. The rest of manuscript contains charts and formulas on the rules of inheritance.
- Title (Romanized): [Ilm-i Faraiz] Title (English): [Science of inheritance] Alternative titles: Incipit: Tereke-i meyyite hukuk-i erbaa taalûk ider, Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 184; 90 leaves: paper; 223 x 157 mm. bound to 224 x 159 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: green marble paper on boards, with burgundy leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked words in red; charts and formulae. (Box 50)
  The manuscript contains two brief treatises on inheritance, up to leaf 9b, and the first two begin: Tereke-i meyyite hukuk-i erbaa taalûk ider. The rest of manuscript contains charts and formulas on the rules of inheritance.
- Title (Romanized): Ensab-i asere-i mübessire Title (English): The genealogies of the ten bearers of glad tidings Alternative titles: ????? ???? ?????, Ensabü'n-nebi ve asere-i mübessire, Date: 1820; Manuscript number: 185; 156 leaves: paper; 234 x 145 mm. bound to 232 x 145 mm.; Layout: 25 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Grey paper on boards, with burgundy leather around the edges, and fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 50)
  The history and genealogy of the prophet Mu?ammad, his household, and some of the early companions (including Caliphs).
- Title (Romanized): Irsâdü'l-mürid ile'l-murad fî tercemet-i Mirsâdi'l-ibâd Title (English): Guiding the seeker towards what is desired by translating The path of bondsmen Alternative titles: ????? ?????? ??? ?????? ?? ????? ????? ??????, Date: [17--]; Manuscript number: 186; 256 leaves: paper; 230 x 161 mm. bound to 229 x 159 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Black leather, blind-stamped, with pink paste-downs, and fore-edge flap; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 51)
- Title (Romanized): [Vakiyat] Title (English): [Occurrences], Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 187; 152 leaves: paper; 224 x 166 mm. bound to 223 x 165 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Yellowed marble paper on boards, with leather stripe over spine, and yellow paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; some marginalia; leaves missing from the end. (Box 51)
  The author's last name is spelled ??? ???? in the Arabic script, and the Arabic version of his grandfather's name is given as ?????. Presumably the pronunciation could also be Gazizade or Guzzazade.
  An account of the life of the author's grandfather who was a great Sufi master.
- Title (Romanized): Maalimü'l-yakin fî siret-i seyyidi'l-mürselin Title (English): Certain knowledge in the biography of the lord of prophets Alternative titles: ????? ?????? ?? ???? ??? ????????, Date: [16--]; Manuscript number: 188; 288 leaves: paper; 213 x 136 mm. bound to 214 x 135 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with marble paste-downs, and fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 51)
  Biography of the prophet Mu?ammad, translated into Turkish from an Arabic original entitled al-Mawahib al-laduniyah bi al-mina? al-Mu?ammadiyah by A?mad ibn Mu?ammad Qas?allani (1447 or 8-1517 or 18), and dedicated to a vizier named Mehmet Pasa (3b).
- Title (Romanized): Vahdetname Title (English): Book of unity Alternative titles: ???? ????, Date: [15--]; Manuscript number: 189; 213 leaves: paper; 202 x 142 mm. bound to 204 x 148 mm.; Layout: 16 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q and Naskh. Binding: Faux black Morocco. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; from 63a onwards in a 17th century hand. (Box 51)
  Sufism: A poem on the world, the soul, and religion. Original composed in 1459 (185b).Manuscript contains a second title as well.
- Title (Romanized): Ta'bir-i [divan-i] Hâf?z Title (English): The interpretation of [the poetic anthology of] ?afi? Alternative titles: [Serh-i] divan-i Hâf?z, Date: 1594 April; Manuscript number: 190; 312 leaves: paper; 204 x 123 mm. bound to 203 x 124 mm.; Layout: 25 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Burgundy leather, with gilt decoration, with pink and orange paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 51)
  Sururi's commentary on the Persian poetry of ?afi? (14th century).
- Title (Romanized): Irsâdü'l-mürid ile'l-murad fî tercemet-i Mirsâdü'l-ibâd Title (English): Guiding the seeker towards what is desired by translating The path of bondsmen Alternative titles: ????? ?????? ??? ?????? ?? ????? ????? ??????, Date: 1719; Manuscript number: 191; 209 leaves: paper; 209 x 145 mm. bound to 206 x 148 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with gilt decoration, pink paste-downs, and fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; quires at the beginning separated from binding. (Box 51)
- Title (English): [For pious women], Date: 1693 June; Manuscript number: 192; 124 leaves: paper; 212 x 146 mm. bound to 204 x 148 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap; badly frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; leaves missing from the beginning. (Box 52)
  The text seems to have been written for women, for it contains topics such as the rights of women over men, or the virtues of pious women, all illustrated with apt stories.
- Title (English): [Lyrics and scales], Date: [19--]; Manuscript number: 193; 178 leaves: paper; 214 x 136 mm. bound to 215 x 135 mm.; Layout: Average 10 lines of text per page, slanted. Script: Riqa. Binding: Black Morocco with green paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b illuminated; blank leaves throughout. (Box 52)
  A collection of lyrics for songs in various musical scales (makam).
- Title (Romanized): Bag-i bihist Title (English): Garden of paradise Alternative titles: ??? ????, Date: [16--]?; Manuscript number: 194; 236 leaves: paper; 212 x 144 mm. bound to 210 x 150 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Cloth on boards, with leather stripe over spine, and fore-edge flap; badly frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b illuminated; some quires separating; water damage. (Box 52)
- Title (Romanized): Tebyînü'l-meram Title (English): Making the meaning clear Alternative titles: ????? ??????, Date: 1736 January; Manuscript number: 195; 191 leaves: paper; 201 x 139 mm. bound to 200 x 150 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with leather stripe over fore-edge and spine; marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b illuminated; marginalia. (Box 52)
  A commentary on a treatise called Beý ve sera (buying and purchasing) by Hamza Efendi. The volume also contains the text by Hamza Efendi, written in a nineteenth-century hand.
- Title (Romanized): [Min Künhü'l-ahbar] Uniform title: Künh ül-ahbar Title (English): [From the Cream of histories], Date: 1652 January; Manuscript number: 196; 182 leaves: paper; 197 x 140 mm. bound to 198 x 140 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Brown leather with yellow paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 52)
  The manuscript contains sections on the Umayyid, Abbasid, and Timurid dynasties from the famous 16th century Ottoman history. There is a second title in the volume as well, a continuation of Ibrahim Peçevî's history, originally composed in 1651.
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i] Mesail-i garibe Title (English): [Translation of] Strange problems, Date: 1714; Manuscript number: 197; 231 leaves: paper; 203 x 133 mm. bound to 202 x 133 mm.; Layout: Average 16 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Burgundy leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap, and green canvass paste-downs; spine separated. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red or gilt borders; 4b, 14b, 20b, 29b, 33b, 45b, 50b, 160b, 172b, 188b, 203b, illuminated; 192b illustrated wit map of human tongue; marginalia. (Box 52)
  Translation of a treatise on prayer, originally composed by a certain Abdürrahim Efendi. The manuscript contains eighteen other titles, all in Turkish, short and long, in prose and verse, on religious matters including works by ?asan al-Ba?ri, Brigivi, Sanusi.
- Title (Romanized): Teshilü'l-mikat Title (English): Simplifying the fixed time Alternative titles: ????? ???????, Date: 1683 April; Manuscript number: 198; 93 leaves: paper; 197 x 140 mm. bound to 198 x 140 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page, slanted. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded yellow/green paper on boards, with leather stripe over spine, ad fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; sheets of paper laid and tipped in. (Box 52)
  The author says that he was the time-keeper of the Hakani Selimi mosque (1b).
  Treatise on the measurement of time based on the positions of the sun in the sky. The manuscript contains two other titles.
- Title (Romanized): H?snu'l-hasîn fî menheci'd-dîn Title (English): Impregnable fortress on the path of religion Alternative titles: ??? ?????? ?? ???? ?????, Date: 1680; Manuscript number: 199; 193 leaves: paper; 199 x 139 mm. bound to 195 x 145 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page, slanted. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; insect damage. (Box 53)
  Turkish translation of Mu?ammad ibn Mu?ammad Ibn al-Jazari's (1350-1429) ?u?n al-?a?in min kalam Sayyid al- Mursalin, dealing with Hadiths about prayer, charity, etc. The present translation is other than the Turkish translation of the same original by Yahya b. Abdülkerim.
- Title (Romanized): Zuhr-i Ahiret Title (English): Treasure-store for the afterlife Alternative titles: ??? ????, Date: [16--]; Manuscript number: 200; 32 leaves: paper; 196 x 140 mm. bound to 195 x 141 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Soft burgundy leather with marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; quires separated. (Box 53)
  Author also calls himself Seyyid Hasan Hac? Oglu and Aksarayi. Late 19th/early 20th century note in pencil on 1a calls him Hasan R?za Aksarayî.
  Note dated 1735 on 1a
  An ode praising the prophet, developed as a commentary on the Burdah of al-Bu?iri. Original composed in 1644 during the reign of the Ottoman Sultan Ibrahim I (1640-1648).
- Title (Romanized): [Vak'a-name] Uniform title: Vakia-nâme-i Veysî Efendi Title (English): [Book of occurrences] Alternative titles: Vaqah'namah, Date: [Before 1707]?; Manuscript number: 201; 143 leaves: paper; 191 x 96 mm. bound to 195 x 108 mm.; Layout: Average 23 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q and Naskh. Binding: Soft brown leather; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, parts closed in gilt borders; 18b illuminated. (Box 53)
  A collection of historical occurrences of unrest, written by the author for the Ottoman Sultan Ahmet I (1603-1617). The manuscript contains another prose title, as well as copies of royal correspondences, verse and prose works of the poet Cevrî (Ibrahim, 17th cent.), and a treatise on inheritance. The latest date occurs on a number of leaves that may or may not have been part of any of the other fragments.
- Title (Romanized): [Pend-i Rical] Title (English): [Advice to men], Date: 1788 May; Manuscript number: 202; 142 leaves: paper; 215 x 154 mm. bound to 217 x 159 mm.; Layout: Average 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black leather, blind-stamped; torn and frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; water damage; leaves missing from the beginning. (Box 53)
  Author's name and title penciled by a modern hand on 1a. DP
  Ethical poem with stories. Several shorter prose and verse pieces are appended to the back, including Cevahirü'l-Islam (131a) and Kitap-i Ibrahim Edhem (137a- 140b). To these are added short poems (141ba-142b) dated 18 November 1790.
- Title (Romanized): Dürretü't-taç Uniform title: Dürret üt-taç Title (English): Pearl of the crown Alternative titles: ??? ?????, Dürret üt- taç fi sahib-ül miraç, Durrat al-taj, Date: 1727; Manuscript number: 203; 257 leaves: paper; 202 x 115 mm. bound to 197 x 112 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Black leather, with gilt decoration, and marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, bound in gilt borders, 1b, 130b, and 132 illuminated. (Box 53)
- Title (Romanized): Risale-i tevhîd Uniform title: Risâle-i tevhîd Title (English): Treatise on unity Alternative titles: ????? ?????, Date: 1652; Manuscript number: 204; 125 leaves: paper; 195 x 145 mm. bound to 192 x 140 mm.; Layout: Average 16 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Burgundy leather, blind-stamped, with marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; water damage; quires separated from the spine. (Box 53)
  A treatise on sufism in ten chapters. There are three other titles in the manuscript, all by the same author (see Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. I: 225-226). The date and the scribe are for title 3 only.
- Title (Romanized): Nasihatü'l-müslimin Title (English): Advice for Muslims Alternative titles: ????? ????????, Date: 1761 April; Manuscript number: 205; 271 leaves: paper; 200 x 135 mm. bound to 197 x 132 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, inlaid; frayed, worn, and separated. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders, 1b illuminated. (Box 54)
  Form of author's name from manuscript 210.
  Commentary on a work entitled Vasiyetname written by the 16th-century theologian Mehmet Birgivi.
- Title (Romanized): [Macmua-i siir] Title (English): [Collection of poetry], Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 206; 246 leaves: paper; 211 x 148 mm. bound to 208 x 147 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh and Riqa. Binding: Black leather, blind-stamped, with yellow paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink; table of contents; leaves missing from the beginning. (Box 54)
  A collection of lyrics, mostly in Turkish, but a few in Persian, of poets such as Hayâlî (d. 1557), Usûli, d. 1534, Kha?a'i (Shah Ismail I, 1487-1524), Kul(?) Nesîmî (17th cent.), Nev'î (1533-1599), Baki (1526-1600), etc.
- Title (Romanized): Tevarih Uniform title: Tarih-i Nisanc? Mehmed Pasa Title (English): Histories Alternative titles: Tarih-i Nisanc? Mehmet? ??????, Date: 1766 September; Manuscript number: 207; 138 leaves: paper; 227 x 158 mm. bound to 226 x 154 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, inlaid, with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 54)
  Universal history, covering the events up to the enthronement of the Ottoman Sultan Selim II on Sunday 29 September 1566 C.E.
- Title (Romanized): [Resail] Title (English): [Treatises], Date: 1819 August; Manuscript number: 208; 47 leaves: paper; 204 x 1468 mm. bound to 202 x 145 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Marble paper on boards with brown leather stripe over spine, fore-edge flap, and orange paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 54)
  A collection of treatises by Erzincanî on Sufism. The manuscript contains six title in all.